A Finding Aid to the Elmer Bischoff papers, 1914-1990, in the Archives of American Art AAA.biscelme
Archives of American Art
Elmer Bischoff papers
1914-1990
AAA.biscelme
Archives of American Art
3.8 Linear feet
The papers of San Francisco painter and arts instructor Elmer Bischoff measure 3.8 linear feet and date from 1914 to 1990, with the bulk of the material dating from the late 1950s to the mid-1980s. Found within the papers are biographical materials, scattered correspondence, notes and notebooks, teaching and student files, printed materials, artwork and two sketchbooks, and photographs and negatives of Bischoff, his family, post World War II Europe, and artwork studies.
Bischoff, Elmer, 1916-1991
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1930-1990 (Box 1, 0.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1956-1990 (Box 1, 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Notes and Notebooks, 1976-1989 (Box 1, 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: University Files, 1954-1990 (Box 2, 0.4 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1941-1990 (Box 3-6, 1.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1958, undated (Box 7-8, 0.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographic Materials, 1914-1990 (Box 9, 0.2 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Elmer Bischoff (1916-1991) was an influential painter and arts instructor in the San Francisco Bay Area figurative art movement that emerged in the early 1950s.
Bischoff grew up in Berkeley, California and attended the University of California (UC) at Berkeley, receiving his Master of Arts in 1939. During the Great Depression, he became involved with the Federal Art Project and taught ceramics at an arts center in Sacramento, California. During World War II, he served in the US Air Force and was stationed in England as an intelligence officer. When he returned to California in 1945, he taught at the California School of Fine Arts (now known as San Francisco Art Institute) with Richard Diebenkorn, David Park, Mark Rothko, Clyfford Still, and Ad Reinhardt. He resigned from the school in the early 1950s when he took up figurative painting, but returned in 1956 to head the graduate program. In 1963 he became an associate professor at UC Berkeley, and was promoted to full professor in 1965, where he stayed until he retired in 1985.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Two items on reel 2787 were donated in 1974 by Elmer Bischoff. His papers were donated in 1991 by his widow, Adelie Bischoff.
Related Archival Materials note
Among other resources relating to the Elmer Bischoff papers are two oral histories with Bischoff; one conducted in 1965 by Mary McChesney and the other conducted in 1977 by Paul J. Karlstrom.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of San Francisco painter and arts instructor Elmer Bischoff measure 3.8 linear feet and date from 1914 to 1990, with the bulk of the material dating from the late 1950s to the mid-1980s. Found within the papers are biographical materials, scattered correspondence, notes and notebooks, teaching and student files, printed materials, artwork and two sketchbooks, and photographs and negatives of Bischoff, his family, post World War II Europe, and artwork studies.
Biographical materials document jurying on art prize committees, interviews with others, lists of names and addresses, and biographical materials. Scattered correspondence is with Staempfli Gallery, organizations, and artists. Notes and notebooks document people Bischoff kept in touch with, as well as day-to-day occurrences in his life, including health and travel. University files document Bischoff’s years as a professor at UC Berkeley, as well as papers written about him and notes from his days as a student at UC Berkeley. The bulk of the collection consists of printed material documenting exhibitions, magazines and newspapers where Bischoff's work was profiled, and materials that document his personal interests. Artwork and two sketchbooks contain drawings, watercolors, and collages by Bischoff. Photographs are of Bischoff, his family, travel, and art resource photographs.
Staempfli Gallery (New York, N.Y.); University of California, Berkeley -- Faculty; University of California, Berkeley. (Students); Art - Study and teaching; Collages; Drawings; Interviews; Painters -- California -- San Francisco; Watercolors
- Biographical Materials, 1930-1990; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, 9
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials date from 1930-1990 and document Bischoff’s professional life. Included are drafts of his resume and curriculum vitae, a transcript from a speech, mailing lists and address books, material from jurying for art prize committees, and Bischoff’s junior high school yearbook. The bulk of the biographical materials are made up by bio-bibliography supplemental material, which was material collected on an annual basis, possibly for tenure purposes, in order to update faculty biographies at UC Berkeley. The bio-bibliography supplemental material includes curriculum vitae drafts, expense reports, letters from galleries, news releases, notices of awards, sales contracts, purchase orders, proposals, a request for appointment to the Institute of Creative Arts (1966-67), personal services agreements, and a contract for services from the Contractor for the City of Walnut Creek, CA.
  - Bibliography, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bio-Bibliography Supplemental Material, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Biographical Data, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Certificate, National Academy of Design, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 1
  - Clippings and Photographs of Artwork, Gallery Materials, 1957-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Interview with PJK, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interview with Susan Klein, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jurying for Art Prizes, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mailing List, circa 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Metropolitan Museum Questionnaire, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Names and Addresses, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Retirement Party Guest Book, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reviews, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reviews, Fan Letters, 1985 Retrospectives, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - San Francisco State Commencement, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Target: Willard Junior High School Yearbook, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Transcript, Speech at Oakland Museum, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Certificate, National Academy of Design from Box 1, Folder 6, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1956 -1990; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scattered correspondence dates from 1956 -1990 and consists of letters between Bischoff and other artists and Staempfli Gallery.
  - Alphabetical, 1961-1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Archives of American Art, 1966-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Landauer, Susan, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - McCormack, Kathleen, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Staempfli Gallery, 1956-1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Notes and Notebooks, 1976-1989; Series 3; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Notes and notebooks date from 1976-1989 and consist of 12 notebooks and other notes kept by Bischoff. The notes and notebooks contain numerous names and addresses. They also include diary entries about daily life, as well as some of Bischoff’s various personal interests including chess, classical music, and travel.
  - Notes, 1976-1989 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Notebooks, 1976-1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- University Files, 1954-1990; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  University files date from around 1954-1990 and document Bischoff’s career as a professor at UC Berkeley, as well as his time as a student in the UC Extension program. Included are class rolls, material on committees for budgets and research, and university forms. Also included are masters’ theses and student papers written about Elmer Bischoff, some of which were written by students from other universities.
  - California School of Fine Arts, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Class Rolls, 1973-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Research, 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Loose Leaf Organizer, UC Extension, circa 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Student Essays, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - University Forms, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Printed Material, 1941-1990; Series 5; 1.6 Linear feet Box 3-6, 9
  Printed material dates from 1941-1990 and documents Bischoff’s art career, as well as some of his personal interests. Materials include books, newspaper clippings, magazines, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and a deck of tarot cards.
  - Artwork Prints and Postcards, circa 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in box 9, folder 1
  - Book, Modern Art in America, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book, Basic Tap Dancing, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Book, Tarot Classic, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Book, Art in America: New Talent USA, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1958-1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1958-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings Regarding Chess, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Annoucements, 1956-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1941-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1963-1980 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - History Book Club, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Houston Show--Brochures, Clippings, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lectures, 1971-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Magazines, 1955-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Magazines, 1970-1986 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Newspapers, 1958-1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Philips Collection, The, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material regarding Religion, 1966-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Tarot Cards, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Artwork Prints and Postcards (from box 3, folder 1), circa 1953 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Artwork and Sketchbooks, 1958, undated; Series 6; 0.6 Linear feet Box 7-8, OV 10
  Artwork and sketchbooks contains drawings, collages, and watercolors created by Bischoff. Of note are drawings of Bischoff’s contemporaries, David Park and Richard Diebenkorn.
  - Drawings, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Gallery Forms, Paintings and Drawings, circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
  - Oversize Sketchbook, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Artwork, undated (Box 9, Folder 2-4)
  - Matted Sketches, 1958 (Box OV 10, Folder 1)
- Photographic Materials, 1914-1990; Series 7; 0.2 Linear feet Box 8
  Photographic materials consist of developed prints and negatives of Elmer Bischoff himself, as well as family photos. Most notable are photographs of post-World War II Europe, taken by Bischoff after he served in the Air Force, and a signed photograph of Captain A.W. Nelson, author of “Yankee Swanson.”
  - Bischoff, Elmer, circa 1974-1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bischoff, Elmer, circa 1980s (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Family Campout, 1982-1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Family Photographs, 1914-1990 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Post-World War II Europe, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
  - Test Photos of Paintings, Lights, Film, and Notes, 1979-1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)